<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<!--<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="project-plan-render.xsl"?>-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="http://www.eclipse.org/projects/project-plan.xsl"?>
<p:plan plan-format="1.0" xmlns:p="http://www.eclipse.org/project/plan" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" name="Business Intelligence and Reporting Tools (BIRT)">
   <p:release projectid="birt" version="4.3"/>
   <p:introduction><html:div><html:p>This document lays out the feature and API set for the next major feature release of the Eclipse BIRT project after 4.2, designated release 4.3 and code-named Kepler. 
This release is occurring simultaneously with the 4.3 release. The 4.3 release release contains significant new feature work, 
while the 3.8 release focuses on stability and bug fixes.</html:p>

<html:p>Plans do not materialize out of nowhere, nor are they entirely static. To ensure the planning process is transparent and open to the entire
Eclipse community, plans are posted in an embryonic form and then revised from time to time throughout the release cycle.</html:p>
<html:p>The first part of the plan deals with the important matters of release deliverables, release milestones, target operating environments, and
release-to-release compatibility. These are all things that need to be clear for any release, even if no features were to change.</html:p>
<html:p>The remainder of the plan consists of plan items for the projects under the Eclipse BIRT project. Each plan item covers a feature or API that
is to be added, or some aspect that is to be improved. Each plan item has its own entry in the Eclipse bugzilla database, with a title and a concise
summary(usually a single paragraph) that explains the work item at a suitably high enough level so that everyone can readily understand what the work item
is without having to understand the nitty-gritty detail.</html:p><html:p>Please send comments about this draft plan to the <html:a href="mailto:birt-dev@eclipse.org">BIRT Developer</html:a> mailing list.</html:p></html:div></p:introduction>
   <p:release_deliverables>
	<html:p>This release of BIRT will focus on providing the same downloads as BIRT 4.2.</html:p>
   </p:release_deliverables>
   <p:release_milestones>
      <p:preamble>
         <html:div><html:p>The BIRT 4.3 Release will follow the Kepler simultaneous release milestone schedule.
		  </html:p>			
			<html:p>For information about new features assigned to each milestone please refer to the <html:a href="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs">bugzilla
			database</html:a>. The bugzilla database will be updated on an ongoing basis as the plan progresses.</html:p>
		</html:div>
      </p:preamble>
      <p:milestone date="3/22/2013" milestone="M6"><html:div>4.3 M6</html:div></p:milestone>
      <p:milestone date="5/10/2013" milestone="M7"><html:div>4.3 M7</html:div></p:milestone>
      <p:milestone date="5/24/2013" milestone="RC1"><html:div>4.3 RC1</html:div></p:milestone>
      <p:milestone date="5/31/2013" milestone="RC2"><html:div>4.3 RC2</html:div></p:milestone>
      <p:milestone date="6/7/2013" milestone="RC3"><html:div>4.3 RC3</html:div></p:milestone>
      <p:milestone date="6/14/2013" milestone="RC4"><html:div>4.3 RC4</html:div></p:milestone>
      <p:milestone date="6/26/2013" milestone="Release"><html:div>4.3 Release</html:div></p:milestone>
      
   </p:release_milestones>

 <p:target_environments>
     	<html:p>In order to remain current, each release of an Eclipse project targets reasonably current versions of underlying operating environments and
		other Eclipse projects on which it depends.</html:p>
		<html:p>Most of Eclipse, and all of BIRT, is "pure" Java code and has no direct dependence on the underlying operating system. For BIRT, the chief
		dependence is on the Eclipse Platform, Graphical Editor Framework (GEF), Modeling Framework (EMF), and on the Java 2 Platform that runs it. </html:p>
		<html:p>The Eclipse BIRT 4.3 release depends on the following compatibility stacks:</html:p>

		<html:p><html:b>BIRT 4.3 Reference Stack for Java SE 7</html:b></html:p>
		<html:ul>
  		<html:li>Java SE 7</html:li>
  		<html:li>Eclipse Platform Runtime Binary 4.3</html:li>
  		<html:li>Graphical Editor Framework (GEF) Runtime 3.9</html:li>
  		<html:li>Eclipse Modeling Framework (EMF) 2.9</html:li>
  		<html:li>Data Tools Platform Project (DTP) 1.11 </html:li>
  		<html:li>Web Tools Project (WTP) 3.5</html:li>
		</html:ul>

		<html:p><html:b>BIRT 4.3 Reference Stack for Java SE 6</html:b></html:p>

		<html:ul>
  		<html:li>Java SE 6</html:li>
  		<html:li>Eclipse Platform Runtime Binary 4.3</html:li>
  		<html:li>Graphical Editor Framework (GEF) Runtime 3.9</html:li>
  		<html:li>Eclipse Modeling Framework (EMF) 2.9</html:li>
  		<html:li>Data Tools Platform Project (DTP) 1.11</html:li>
  		<html:li>Web Tools Project (WTP) 3.5</html:li>
		</html:ul>

		
		<html:p>The Eclipse Platform and BIRT run in a variety of operating environments. Testing is focused on a handful of popular combinations
		of operating system and Java 2 Platform; these are our reference platforms. Eclipse BIRT undoubtedly runs fine in many
		operating environments beyond the reference platforms we test. However, since we do not systematically test them we cannot vouch for them. Problems encountered
		when running Eclipse BIRT on non-reference platforms that cannot be recreated on any reference platform will be given lower priority than problems with
		running Eclipse BIRT on a reference platform.</html:p>

		<html:p>For BIRT 4.3, the project team plans to tests and validate the following reference platforms:</html:p>
		<html:table style="width: 825px; height: 188px;" border="1">
		  <html:tbody>
		    <html:tr bgcolor="#cccccc">
		      <html:th colspan="4">
        	    <html:div align="center"> <html:b><html:font size="+1">Eclipse BIRT Report Framework 4.3 and Eclipse BIRT RCP Report Designer 4.3 Reference Platforms</html:font></html:b></html:div>
		      </html:th>
		    </html:tr>
			<html:tr>
		      <html:td width="205"><html:b>Operating system</html:b></html:td>
		      <html:td width="76"><html:b>Processor architecture</html:b></html:td>
		      <html:td width="59"><html:b>Window system</html:b></html:td>
		      <html:td width="453"><html:b>Java SE</html:b></html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="205">Microsoft Windows 7 SP1, 8, 2008 R2 Server</html:td>
		      <html:td width="76">Intel x86</html:td>
		      <html:td width="59">Win32</html:td>
		      <html:td>Oracle Java SE 6, 7</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="205">Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6.0, 6.1, 6.3<html:br />
		      CENTOS 6.3</html:td>
		      <html:td width="76">Intel x86</html:td>
		      <html:td width="59">GTK</html:td>
		      <html:td width="453">Oracle Java SE 6, 7</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		  </html:tbody>
		</html:table>
		
		<html:br />
		<html:table border="1">
		  <html:tbody>
		    <html:tr bgcolor="#cccccc">
		      <html:th colspan="4">
      	      <html:div align="center"> <html:b><html:font size="+1">Eclipse BIRT Runtime 4.3 and Eclipse BIRT Charts 4.3 Reference Platforms</html:font></html:b></html:div>
		      </html:th>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="205"><html:b>Operating system</html:b></html:td>
		      <html:td width="76"><html:b>Processor architecture</html:b></html:td>
		      <html:td width="59"><html:b>Window system</html:b></html:td>
		      <html:td width="453"><html:b>Java SE</html:b></html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="205">Microsoft Windows 7, 8, 2008 R2 Server</html:td>
		      <html:td width="76">Intel x86</html:td>
		      <html:td width="59">Win32*</html:td>
		      <html:td width="453">Oracle Java SE 6,7</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="205">Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6.0<html:br />
		      CENTOS 6.3
		      </html:td>
		      <html:td width="76">Intel x86</html:td>
		      <html:td width="59">GTK*</html:td>
		      <html:td width="453">Oracle Java SE 6, 7</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="205">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 9</html:td>
		      <html:td width="76">Intel x86</html:td>
		      <html:td width="59">YaST*</html:td>
		      <html:td width="453">Oracle Java SE 6, 7</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		  </html:tbody>
		</html:table>
		<html:div>*Window system only required when displaying charts within SWT or SWING windows.</html:div><html:br />
		<html:br />
		<html:table border="1">
		  <html:tbody>
		    <html:tr bgcolor="#cccccc">
		      <html:th colspan="1">
      		     <html:div align="center"> <html:b><html:font size="+1">BIRT Application Server Reference Platform</html:font></html:b></html:div>
		      </html:th>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Apache Tomcat 6.0.16, 7.0.37</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">JBoss AS 7.0.1</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Oracle Weblogic Application Server 10.3, 11</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">IBM Websphere Application Server 7.0, 8.0</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		  </html:tbody>
		</html:table>

		<html:br />

		<html:table border="1">
		  <html:tbody>
		    <html:tr bgcolor="#cccccc">
		      <html:th colspan="1">
      		      <html:div align="center"> <html:b><html:font size="+1">BIRT JDBC Reference Platforms</html:font></html:b></html:div>
		      </html:th>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">MySQL Connector/J 3.x JDBC driver</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Derby V10.5.1.1 JDBC driver</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Actuate DataDirect JDBC drivers</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		  </html:tbody>
		</html:table>

                <html:br />

		<html:table border="1">
		  <html:tbody>
		    <html:tr bgcolor="#cccccc">
		      <html:th colspan="1">
      		      <html:div align="center"> <html:b><html:font size="+1">BIRT Browsers and Viewers Reference Platforms</html:font></html:b></html:div>
		      </html:th>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Mozilla Firefox 19 (Linux and Windows)</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Google Chrome 25 (Windows)</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Microsoft Internet Explorer 8, 9 (Windows)</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Safari 5 (Windows)</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		    <html:tr>
		      <html:td width="405">Adobe Acrobat Reader 8, 9, 10 (Windows)</html:td>
		    </html:tr>
		</html:tbody>
		</html:table>
		<html:br />


		<html:span style="font-weight: bold;"><html:a name="CommunityOperatingEnvironments" id="CommunityOperatingEnvironments">Community
		Tested Operating Environments</html:a></html:span>
		<html:p>Due to the finite resources available to the BIRT project, we would like to encourage the BIRT community to contribute to testing BIRT in
		operating environments other than those listed as target operating environments for the 4.3 release of BIRT and to share this
		information with the rest of the community. If you have been able to test BIRT in a non-targeted operating environment please take a few
		minutes to update this <html:a href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/BIRT_Community_Tested_Operating_Environments_for_4.3">wiki
		page</html:a> and report this information there. If you have encountered bugs during your testing, please report these in
		bugzilla.</html:p>
	<p:internationalization>
          <html:div>
          	<html:p>Eclipse is designed as the basis for internationalized products. The user interface elements provided by the various Eclipse projects, including
			dialogs and error messages, are externalized. The English strings for BIRT are provided as the default resource bundles. Translations are provided
			with this release for French (fr_FR), German (de_DE), Spanish (es_ES), Japanese (ja_JP), Simplified Chinese (zh_CN), and Korean (ko_KR).</html:p>
		</html:div>
     </p:internationalization>
   </p:target_environments>
   <p:compatibility_with_previous_releases>
       <html:div>		
       	<html:p>BIRT 4.3 will be compatible with earlier versions of BIRT to the greatest extent possible. The nature and scope of some of the key plan items for
		BIRT 4.3 are such that the only feasible solutions might break compatibility. In other regards, BIRT 4.3 will be compatible with 3.x, 2.x and 1.x. We also
		aim to minimize the effort required to port an existing plug-in to the 4.3 APIs.</html:p>
		<html:b>Compatibility of Release 4.3 with Prior Releases</html:b>

		<html:p>BIRT 4.3 will be compatible with prior releases of BIRT unless noted otherwise. The detailed compatibility statement is listed below.
		In this statement, "BIRT" refers to all BIRT components: BIRT Report Framework, BIRT Runtime, and BIRT Chart SDK.</html:p>
		<html:p><html:b>API Contract Compatibility:</html:b> BIRT 4.3 will be upwards contract-compatible with BIRT prior releases to the greatest
		extent possible. All incompatibility exceptions will be documented.Downward contract compatibility is not supported. There is no guarantee that
		compliance with BIRT 4.3 APIs will ensure compliance with prior BIRT release APIs. Refer to general Eclipse document on <html:a href="http://wiki.eclipse.org/index.php/Evolving_Java-based_APIs">Evolving
		APIs</html:a> for a discussion of the kinds of API changes that maintain contract compatibility.</html:p>

		<html:p>The BIRT Chart UI API 4.3 is compatible with the 3.x and 2.x.x API's but not compatible with the v1.x APIs due to a full redesign of the
		Chart UI in the BIRT 2.0 release.</html:p>

		<html:p><html:b>Binary (plug-in) Compatibility:</html:b> The BIRT 4.3 plug-in framework will be upwards binary-compatible with prior BIRT release plug-ins to
		the greatest extent possible. Downward plug-in compatibility is not supported. Plug-ins for BIRT 4.3 will not be usable in prior BIRT
		releases. Extension plug-ins for prior BIRT releases will be upwards binary-compatible with BIRT 4.3.</html:p>

		<html:p><html:b>Source Compatibility:</html:b> BIRT 4.3 will be upwards source-compatible with prior BIRT releases to the greatest
		extent possible. This means that source files written to use prior BIRT release APIs will successfully compile and run against BIRT 4.3 APIs. Downward
		source compatibility is not supported. If source files use new BIRT APIs, they will not be usable with an earlier version of BIRT.</html:p>

		<html:p><html:b>Report Design Compatibility:</html:b>BIRT 4.3 will be upwards report design compatible with prior BIRT releases unless
		noted otherwise. This means that reports created with prior BIRT releases can be successfully opened by BIRT 4.3 and upgraded to a 4.3 format.</html:p>

		<html:p><html:b>Non-compliant usage of API's: </html:b> All non-API methods and classes, and certainly everything in a package with "internal" in its name, are
		considered implementation details which may vary between operating environment and are subject to change without notice. Client plug-ins that directly depend
		on anything other than what is specified in the BIRT API are inherently unsupportable and receive no guarantees about compatibility within a
		single release much less with an earlier releases.</html:p>
	</html:div>
   </p:compatibility_with_previous_releases>

   <p:themes_and_priorities>
     <p:preamble>
         <html:div>
         	<html:p>Continuing on the themes for previous releases of BIRT, the BIRT project's overriding release 4.3 theme remains extending the Eclipse platform to
			provide infrastructure and tools that allow application developers to design, deploy, generate and view reports within their applications. In this
			context,the BIRT project also adopts and supports key themes within the overall Eclipse planning process.</html:p>
         </html:div>
     </p:preamble>
     <p:theme name="Support access to MongoDB">
        <p:description>
        	<html:div>Currently BIRT natively supports Flat File (CSV, SSV, PSV and TSV), JDBC Textual, JDBC Graphical Query Builder, XML, and Web Service data sources. 
                This project provides the ability for BIRT developers to access data contained in MongoDB, a popular NoSQL repository.
        	</html:div>
        </p:description>
        <p:proposed bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=402794"></p:proposed>
     </p:theme>
     <p:theme name="Support access to Apache Cassandra">
        <p:description>
        	<html:div>This project provides the ability for BIRT developers to access data in Apache Cassandra.
        	</html:div>
        </p:description>
        <p:proposed bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=402795"></p:proposed>
     </p:theme>
     <p:theme name="Office 2010 PowerPoint and Word Emitters">
        <p:description>
        	<html:div>This project aims to provide the developer with the ability to output BIRT reports in Office 2010 PowerPoint and Word formats.
        	</html:div>
	</p:description>  
        <p:proposed bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=402796"></p:proposed>      	
        <p:proposed bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=402797"></p:proposed>      	
     </p:theme>
     <p:theme name="Enhanced Microsoft Excel Emitter">
        <p:description>
        	<html:div>This project aims to provide the developer with an enhanced Microsoft Excel emitter.
        	</html:div>
	</p:description>  
        <p:proposed bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=402962"></p:proposed>      	
     </p:theme>
     <p:theme name="Easy to Access POJO's">
        <p:description>
        	<html:div>This project makes it easy for BIRT developers to access data from POJO data sources.
        	</html:div>
		</p:description>        	
        <p:proposed bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=402798"></p:proposed>      	
     </p:theme>
     <p:theme name="Support Easy Inclusion of Client Side JavaScript Libraries">
        <p:description>
        	<html:div>This project makes it easy for advanced BIRT developers to include JavaScript libraries in a BIRT report.
        	</html:div>
		</p:description>        	
        <p:proposed bugzilla="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/show_bug.cgi?id=403403"></p:proposed>      	
     </p:theme>
   </p:themes_and_priorities>

   <p:appendix name=": Help Wanted">
     <html:div>We welcome any contributions from the community towards the BIRT project. This help can be in the form of adding new functionality to BIRT, 
     submitting bug fixes/enhancements to the current BIRT code and testing BIRT on new platforms. 
     <html:br />Please refer to <html:a href="https://bugs.eclipse.org/bugs/buglist.cgi?keywords=helpwanted;query_format=advanced;keywords_type=allwords;bug_status=NEW;classification=BIRT;product=BIRT">this bugzilla query</html:a> for 
     the list of enhancements that we need help on. 
     For more information on how you can contribute to the BIRT project, refer to <html:a href="http://www.eclipse.org/birt/phoenix/project/contribute.php">How to Contribute to the BIRT Project</html:a>
     </html:div>
   </p:appendix>	

</p:plan>
